Okay, בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף *daf* is דף ד *daf
daled* for עבודה זרה avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*. We are picking up
at the bottom of ג עמוד ב *Gimmel Amud Beis* where we're
deep in the middle of the אגדתא Agaddata, *Agadata* here.
And you know, we spoke about, you know, how all the nations
will try to justify their actions. It's all about תורה Torah *Torah*.
God will מופסה *makf* them, you know, even, you know, what you
did you did for yourselves
and anyway it's all for Me. And then God wants, fine, you
want, I'll give you one last attempt to see if you can
keep the מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvos*. Gives them an easy מצווה *mitzvah*, the
מצוות mitzvos סוכה *Mitzvas Sukkah*. They totally blow it. Okay. So, and
then God laughs at them. You know, and then we got into
a whole digression about God laughing. Okay. So now we pick up
here, we pick up where it says אמר amar... רבי Rebbi לוי
*Amar Rabbi Levi*. It is about six, one two three, about eight
lines before the lines get wide on ג עמוד ב *Gimmel Amud
Beis* at two words in, three words in with an asterisk.
אמר רבי Rebbi לוי *Amar Rabbi Levi*, כל הפוסק מדברי תורה Torah
ועוסק
בדברי
שיחה מאכילים לו גחלי רתמים *Kol haposek midivrei Torah ve'osek bedivrei sicha
machilin lo gachalei resamim*. Says Rabbi Levi, whoever interrupts the words of
תורה Torah *Torah* and involves himself in, you know, frivolous talk, they
feed him like, you know, burning hot coals. שנאמר shene'emar, הקוטפים מלוח
עלי שיח *Shene'emar hakotfim maluach alei siach*. Those who grab מלוח *maluach*,
which usually means like some salted thing, but Rashi says it's מי
לוחות *mei luchot* from the words that were written on the tablets.
You know, so you sort of pull yourself away from the words
of the tablets עלי שיח *alei siach* for normal, this is the
way it's being read, not the literal meaning, for like frivolous talk.
ושרש רתמים לחמם *Veshoresh resamim lachmam*. So the root of like the,
you know, these burning hot coals is the, will be your bread.
אמר ריש לקיש *Amar Reish Lakish*, כל העוסק בתורה בלילה *Kol ha'osek
baTorah balayla*.
Anybody, because you know this is all picked up on the fact
that God is spending His time in the morning learning תורה Torah
*Torah* and then He's spending His time in the afternoon, like late
afternoon, teaching תורה Torah? *Torah* to these infants who died, you know,
at a young age, you know, who infant, you know, who died
in their infancy. So that seems to be the tie-in here.
So where were we?
So it says like this. אמר ריש לקיש *Amar Reish Lakish*, כל
העוסק בתורה בלילה הקדוש ברוך הוא מושך עליו חוט של חסד ביום
*Kol ha'osek baTorah balayla HaKadosh Baruch Hu moshech alav chut shel chesed
bayom*. Anybody who learns תורה Torah, *Torah* at night, הקדוש ברוך הוא
*HaKadosh Baruch Hu* causes a string of charm to wrap around the
person in the day. שנאמר shenemar יומם יצוה ה' חסדו ובלילה שירה
עמי *Shene'emar yomam yetzaveh Hashem chasdo uvalayla shiro imi*. In the day
God will command His kindness, or I think here it's sort of
like, you know, His finding charm in the, you know, favor in
the eyes of people. ובלילה שירה עמי *Uvalayla shiro imi*. And at
night His song is with me. And now that was a quote
we had before about at night His song is with me because
it was a mention what does God do at night? He hears
the song of the heavenly angels. Okay. מה טעם יומם יצוה ה'
חסדו *Ma ta'am yomam yetzaveh Hashem chasdo*? Why does God make, have
give this person, you know,
favor in the eyes of people in the day? משום דבלילה שירה
עמו *Mishum devalayla shiro imo*. Because at night His song is with
him. So first of all it's very beautiful that it sort of
talks about תורה Torah. *Torah* as a type of a שירה *shira*,
a song, you know, as a way of, you know, brings joy,
as a way of praising God, as a way of expressing your
connection to God. You know, the idea of תורה Torah. *Torah* as
a שירה *shira* is something that Rav Soloveitchik, you know, has developed
at great, at great length. Also the idea about doing it at
night and getting reward in the day, you know, the מהרש"א *Maharsha*
says normally somebody stays up late at night they look miserable during
the day, you know, the next morning, אוי *oy*, you know, you
look miserable, yeah I was up all night studying. So here it's
saying if you stay up all night studying תורה Torah *Torah* in
the day, you know, it'll be the opposite, you know, everybody, you
know, everybody will say oh you look so good, you look like
you know, you're glowing or something like that. So that's part of
the message. But the other point about תורה Torah *Torah* at night,
you know, is that nighttime is a time, I say this to
my students sometimes, you know, like day your whole day is structured.
So if your job is to be a rabbi you're doing מצוות
Mitzvot *mitzvos* during the day, if your job is to be whatever
you're doing, but at night is sort of quiet, not structured time,
you know, and that's sort of where you, you know, you get
to demonstrate like what are you really about, you know? Like nobody
is around, nobody's looking, you have total ability to focus and you
know, do whatever you want, so if you're learning, grabbing that time
for תורה Torah, *Torah*, you know, that really shows something as opposed
to like, oh woke up in the middle of the night let
me check my emails or go on Facebook or something like that,
you know? So, all right. So,
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel*, מאי דכתיב
Mai dichtiv *mai dicsiv*, what's meant by the verse ותעשה אדם כדגי
הים *Vata'aseh adam kedigei hayam*,
the human beings were like the fish of the sea, כרמש לא
מושל בו *keremes lo moshel bo*, like the crawling things that nobody
was a, was a ruler over them. למה נמשלו בני אדם כדגי
הים *Lama nimshilu benei adam kedigei hayam*? Why are human beings compared
to the fish of the sea? לומר לך מה דגים שבים כיון
שעולים ליבשה מיד Miyad, מתים *Lomar lach mah dagim shebayam kecheivan she'olin
layabasha miyad meisun*, the same way as soon as you take them
to the dry land they immediately die, אף בני אדם כיון שפורשין
מדברי תורה Torah, ומן המצוות מיד מתים *af benei adam kecheivan sheporshin
midivrei Torah umin hamitzvos miyad meisun*. The same with people, and here
of course, you know, Jews, maybe it's non-Jews because the whole point
was that non-Jews aren't involving themselves in תורה Torah, *Torah* and מצוות
Mitzvot *mitzvos*. As soon as they separate themselves from תורה Torah. *Torah*
and מצוות *mitzvos* they will die, presumably like a spiritual death, you
know, that's the classic story, right, about Rabbi Akiva. Akiva, like and
he stood even after the Romans say that you can't learn תורה,
he's basically, he has to keep on learning because otherwise he'll immediately
die. Anyway, but again, the theme here, we're sort of seeming to
have like a little bit generalized, we're talking generally about the importance
of learning תורה all the time, to separate תורה and מצוות, but
that's really the theme. The theme is that the importance here of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah I keep on repeating this, is no longer
the concern it was in the Tannaitic period and certainly in the
biblical period of fighting the pagan
world, it's about and about the idolatry as the draw. It's about
a commitment to a life of תורה and מצוות and the way
the larger world doesn't represent that and can draw you away from
that. Okay, דבר אחר, davar acher, another explanation. מה דגים שבים כיון
שקדרה עליהם חמה מיד מתים, mah dagim shebayam keivan shekadrah aleihem chamah
miyad meisim,
the fish as soon as the sun beats upon them they immediately
die. I don't know what that means. I mean, only after they're
not in the sea. Do fish die in the sea? I mean,
maybe if there's like a volcanic, undersea volcanic eruption and the water
boils. But anyway, presumably it's another way of saying that they're exposed
and out of the water. Anyway, כך בני אדם כיון שקדרה עליהם
חמה מיד מתים. kach bnei adam keivan shekadrah aleihem chamah miyad meisim.
Similarly people, when the sun shines upon them they immediately die and
presumably, I mean, what is this literal? It might mean a line
that we're going to come to which is sort of referring to
like the sun of the future time. Okay, the sun in the
Messianic period. We'll see what that means in a minute. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, אי בעית אימא בעולם הזה, ei ba'is eima
b'olam hazeh, so the גמרא's Gemara next line, it could mean in
this world, ואי בעית אימא לעולם הבא, v'ei ba'is eima l'olam haba,
or it could mean the next one. אי בעית אימא בעולם הזה,
ei ba'is eima b'olam hazeh, this world, כדי רבי חנינא, kide'Rabbi Chanina,
like רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, אמר רבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Chanina,
הכל בידי שמים חוץ מצינים ופחים, Hakol biydei shamayim chutz mitzinim u'pachim,
everything is decreed from heaven except for cold and heat, שנאמר, Shene'emar
צינים ופחים בדרך עקש, tzinim u'pachim bederech ikeish,
cold and heat is in the way of the, is in the
perverted path, שומר נפשו ירחק מהם, shomer nafsho yirchak meihem, the person
who is, who protects himself will distance himself from them. So what
does it mean everything is in the way of, in the hands
of heaven? What it means is the way תוספות Tosafot explains it
is that certain, at least meteorological events are things that you cannot
do anything to protect yourself from. You know, if there's a hurricane,
if there's a tsunami, if there's whatever, or maybe certain illnesses you
can't do anything to protect yourself from. Which is funny because like
we know that you can. But anyway, but things like heat and
cold, those are things that God, it's not decreed whether you will
suffer from the heat or the cold, you have the ability
to control those situations. You have the ability to make sure, if
you know it's going to be a hot day, you sit in
a cool house, you get air conditioning. If it's going to be
a cold day, you know, put on layers. So somebody, so those
are things that you can be aware are happening and prepare yourself
and protect yourself from. So again, it's a little funny that that's
contrasted to everything else in the world, but okay. Anyway, so therefore
you see anyway the dangers of extreme heat and extreme cold and
sort of, so that means also just human beings. Why would a
פסוק pasuk be telling you about the sun? You know, oh, you're
like fish, be prepared about the sun. Yeah, it's just giving you
good medical, or good, not medical, but whatever,
good advice about taking care of your own health. Good health advice.
You know, just know that you're exposed to the elements and take
good care. Okay.
What about a reference to just like the larger fish swallows the
smaller fish?
We're getting there. ואי בעית אימא, v'ei ba'is eima, and if you
want I can tell you, anyway, that was just one thing, good
health advice, being like your good Jewish mother, you're going to go
out like that? Put on a hat, wear double, wear layers. ואי
בעית אימא, v'ei ba'is eima, and if you want I can tell
you, לעולם הבא, l'olam haba, referring to the future time, כדי רבי
שמעון בן לקיש. kide'Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש,
amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, אין גיהנום לעתיד לבוא, ein Gehennom le'asid
lavo, there's no גיהנום Gehennom in the world to come. אלא הקדוש
ברוך הוא מוציא חמה מנרתיקה, ella Hakadosh Baruch Hu motzi chamah minartikah,
what will happen is God will take the sun out of its
like sheath, thank you, right, out of its like protective covering. Right
now we get the sun, but we're not getting the sun at
full power.
Okay. ומקדיר, u'makdir, and he will like burn it down. רשעים נדונים
בה, reshaim nidonim bah, that'll cause the wicked people to be burned
up, to be judged by it, to writhe in pain from the
heat. וצדיקים מתרפאין בה, v'tzaddikim misrapin bah, but for the righteous ones
it'll actually bring healing. You know, you go and you lie in
the sun, it's wonderful, right? Think about people who go and they
lie by the beach. One person has an amazing time, soak up
the rays, the other person is hypersensitive to exposure, and
they're burnt from head to toe, and it was a miserable experience.
רשעים נדונים בה דכתיב, reshaim nidonim bah d'chsiv, top of ד' עמוד
א', daled amud aleph, כי הנה היום בא בוער כתנור, ki hinei
hayom ba bo'er katanur, day is coming to be burning like a
furnace. והיו כל זדים וכל עושה רשעה קש, v'hayu kol zeidim v'chol
osei rish'ah kash, all of the wicked people and all those who
do evil will be like stubble. וליהט אותם היום הבא, v'lihat otam
hayom haba, and it'll burn them up, that future day. אמר ה'
צבאות, amar Hashem Tzevaot, אשר לא יעזוב להם שורש וענף, asher lo
ya'azov lahem shoresh v'anaf, it will not be left for them a
root and a branch. לא שורש בעולם הזה, lo shoresh b'olam hazeh,
no root in this world, ולא ענף לעולם הבא, v'lo anaf l'olam
haba, no branch in the world to come. So that sort of
describes the future time as tremendous heat that will destroy the wicked.
And but צדיקים מתרפאין בה, Tzaddikim misrapin bah, but the righteous will
be healed. דכתיב וזרחה לכם יראי שמי שמש צדקה, d'chsiv v'zorcha lachem
yirei shemi shemesh tzedakah, I will shine for those who fear my
name the sun of righteousness. of righteousness ומרפא בכנפיה u'marpei bichnafeha which
brings healings in its wings. Okay, so, you know, the exact same
thing will do one for the wicked, rather, and it's all basically
like, you know, one way sort of of, like, you know, they
they tell like, you know, there're like, there are stories or fables
that basically give this message. Like one is, you know, somebody goes
and, you know, and he and he dies and they bring him
down to גיהנום Gehinnom to show him what גיהנום Gehinnom is, and
you know, there's got גיהנום Gehinnom is like everybody is sitting at
this table and like, you know, it's a feast and the most
delicious food. The only trouble is like their arms are totally, they
can't bend their arms. So they're like try to reach, they they
reach the food and they can't feed themselves and they're miserable and
they're suffering. And then he goes up to עולם הבא Olam Haba
and he sees the, you know, the exact same thing, this tremendous
feast, but everybody's arms are stuck, but what they're doing is they're
feeding one another. You know? So, so that's a, there's a, there's
a beautiful message there. Anyway, so the point is like the exact
same experience based on who you are. Like another version of it
is, you know, you know, yeah, עולם הבא, Olam Haba, all עולם
הבא Olam Haba is is that your soul goes up to heaven
and whether you're a צדיק tzaddik or a רשע, rasha, and you
spend the entire time sitting in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash learning
תורה for God, you know, with from God, you know, for the
צדיקים tzaddikim it's it's גן עדן Gan Eden and for the רשעים
resha'im it's גיהנום. Gehinnom. So, you know, so anyway,
sounds like good מגיד שיעור, maggid shiur, right?
Well, depends if you can tolerate just sitting and learning all day.
Anyway, okay. ולא עוד אלא שמתעדנין בה v'lo od ela shemisyadnin bah
and
not only that but they like find, you know, what's מתעדנין? misyadnin?
Like they like pleasure, yeah they they get physical pleasure, you know,
their body, they're pampered by it, that's a good word, pampered by
it. שנאמר ויצאתם ופשתם כעגלי מרבק v'yatzasem ufishtem k'eglei marbeik because
you will go out and you will sort of spread out like
the calves of the מרבק, marbeik, some type of I don't know
what that is exactly, some type of a pen. Okay anyway and
רש"י Rashi says it just means that you will, yeah, grow fat.
So, I I think that's the end of that verse.
Okay. דבר אחר מה דגים שבים davar acher mah dagim shevayam
so here's another explanation. What are, what does פשתם pishtem mean? I
spread out, רש"י Rashi says it means, what does רש"י Rashi say
it means? That you'll be
fattened.
דבר אחר מה דגים שבים davar acher mah dagim shevayam another why
reason we're compared to the fish of the sea. כל הגדול מחברו
בולע את חברו kol hagadol mechaveiro bolei'a es chaveiro the,
you know, the big fish swallows small fish. אף בני אדם אלמלא
מוראה של מלכות af bnei adam ilmalei mora'ah shel malchus human beings
were it not for the fear of the government or the kingdom,
כל הגדול מחברו בולע את חברו kol hagadol mechaveiro bolei'a es chaveiro
would be a dog eat dog, fish eat fish world as you
know the stronger one would would destroy the weak. והיינו דתנן v'hainu
d'sanan that's what we taught, רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים אומר הוי מתפלל
בשלומה של מלכות Rabbi Chanina segan hakohanim omer hevei mispallel b'shlomah shel
malchus
pray for the well being the, you know, of the government, שאלמלא
מוראה של מלכות she'ilmalei mora'ah shel malchus were it not for the
fear of the law and of the government, איש את רעהו חיים
בלעו ish es rei'ehu chayim bela'u one person would swallow up his
neighbor. Okay so that's the תפילה לשלום המלכות tefillah l'shlom hamalchus that
is, you know, been a long part of the history of the
liturgy for the for the Jewish people. רבי חנינא בר פפא רמי
Rabbi Chanina bar Papa rami Rabbi Chanina bar Papa showed a contradiction.
כתיב ksiv שדי לא מצאנוהו שגיא כח Shaddai lo m'tzanuhu sagi koach
God
we have not found you to be great in strength. וכתיב uch'siv
but another verse says גדול אדונינו ורב כח gadol adoneinu v'rav koach
great is our our Lord and abundant in strength. וכתיב uch'siv ימינך
ה' נאדרי בכח yeminecha Hashem nedari bakoach your right hand Oh Lord
is you know glorified in strength. So does God have strength? What
does this פסוק pasuk mean that God did not have strength? So
now we're going to tie this back into Jews versus non-Jews, you
know, and future judgment and etc. לא קשיא lo kashya it's not
difficult, כאן בשעת דין כאן בשעת מלחמה. kan b'shas din kan b'shas
milchamah.
It's a time of judgment, right, because also we sort of said
what does God do at different times during the day? He sits
in judgment but then he realizes that the world can't last by
judgment so he gets up from the the seat of judgment and
moves to the seat of compassion.
So when God has to sit in judgment he does not gird
his strength, he does not bring forth his full strength, he holds
himself back. But at the time of war, like the verse, you
know, obviously by שירת הים shiras hayam and maybe they're specifically also
suggesting here about punishment of the wicked nations, that's when God brings
his strength to full force. רבי חמא בר חנינא רמי Rabbi Chama
bar Chanina rami showed a contradiction. כתיב ksiv one verse says חימה
אין לי cheimah ein li
I do not have anger. וכתיב uch'siv but another verse says נוקם
ה' ובעל חימה nokem Hashem uva'al cheimah
God is takes vengeance and is a, you know, is filled with
anger. לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult, כאן בישראל כאן בעובדי
כוכבים. kan b'Yisrael kan b'ovdei kochavim. Again obviously echoing the theme that
we began, is it about how God is going to deal with
the Jews or how God is going to deal with the non-Jews?
That's one answer. רבי חנינא בר פפא אמר Rabbi Chanina bar Papa
amar no,
here's a different explanation. חימה אין לי cheimah ein li I don't
have anger שכבר נשבעתי shekvar nishbati because I have taken an oath,
meaning as רש"י Rashi says, yes I am a person whatever I
am I am filled with anger, you know I I am inclined
to anger but, you know, and maybe justly so because of the
sins etc. so that's the verse that I am בעל חימה ba'al
cheimah but חימה אין לי cheimah ein li but I have Forgone
my anger. I know I'm filled with it but I've forgone it.
Okay. חמה אין לי Chemah Ein Li שכבר נשבעתי Shekvar nishbati because
I have taken oaths, you know, not to destroy the humankind. מי
איני שלא נשבעתי Mi eini shelo nishbati if it would be that
I had not sworn taken the oath, אשמיה בשית Ashmeyah beshait I
would just you know bring like destruction onto the world. Okay, that's
the end of the verse.
Is this specifically later in response to the Jewish people's sins or
is
it just God's general philosophy? Yeah, not exactly clear if the focus
here is about the sins of you know mankind in general, the
world. I mean that fits with the idea that God judges the
world and then God realizes he can't bring the attribute of justice.
So I don't think it's
specifically...
Is he specifically talking about עבודה זרה or is it... No, I
don't think it's specifically Jews versus non-Jews, specifically about the world, you
know. That... but the גמרא's Gemara being clear. Okay. You could read
it about the non-Jews, could be about the Jews. ואמר רבי אלכסנדרי
V'amar Rabbi Alexandri מאי דכתיב Mai dichtiv, ויהיה ביום ההוא אבקש להשמיד
V'haya bayom hahu avakesh l'hashmid here it gets to the non-Jews explicitly.
What's meant by the verse 'and it will be at that day
I will seek to destroy all the nations' אבקש להשמיד את כל
הגוים? Avakesh l'hashmid et kol hagoyim? Right, so this is the idea
God has this anger, he wants to destroy, but he holds himself
back, okay, he takes this oath. So here it's specifically being focused
on the non-Jews. At that day I will I will request I
will ask to destroy all the nations. Desire is obviously what it
means in this context. But the גמרא Gemara has a great play.
אבקש ממי? Avakesh mimi?
Who does God have to ask permission from? God is God! What
do you mean you're going to ask? So אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, God is saying, אבקש בפנקס שלהם. Avakesh b'pinkas
shelahem. I will look in, not I will ask permission, I will
investigate into their you know into their records, into their historical records.
So again echoing back the question about how have they acted in
the past. אם יש להם זכות אפדם, Im yesh lahem zechut efdem,
if they have merit then I will redeem them. ואם לאו, V'im
lav, and if not, אשמידם, Ashmidem,
I will destroy them you know, which is אבקש להשמיד. Avakesh l'hashmid.
So but I will look, but obviously the end result will be
להשמיד L'hashmid because as we've seen, they'll produce their records, they'll produce
their stories, and it will not pass muster. והיינו דאמר רבא, V'hainu
d'amar Rava, that's what Rava says, מאי דכתיב, Mai dichtiv, what's meant
by the verse, אל באיי ישלח יד אם בפידו להן שוע. Al
b'ei yishlach yad im b'pido lahen shoa. So this is a very
difficult verse. It's a verse from איוב, Iyov, so of course go
figure out what it means. Anyway, however he does not desire, he
will send forth his hand, if in the פידו Pido for them
it will be salvation. So what does even this פידו Pido mean?
אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, Amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael,
so God says to the Jewish people, כשאני דן את ישראל אין
אני דן אותם כעובדי כוכבים. Keshe'ani dan et Yisrael ein ani dan
otam k'ovdei kochavim. When I judge the Jewish people, I will not
judge them like I judge the nations. דכתיב Dechtiv by them it
says, עוה עוה עוה אשימנה. Avah avah avah asimenah.
So destruction, destruction, destruction, or turnover, turnover I will make them, meaning
that I will bring all of their punishment on the nations, I
bring it all at once. אלא Ela but rather אני נפרע מהם
כפיד של תרנגולת. Ani nifra mehem k'pid shel tarnegolet.
So I will like like the pecking of a of a chicken
of you know so... Like death by a thousand...
So well yeah that would be the negative of it. But meaning
when they have to be punished, you know, it'll be like tiny
little punishments over... It'll be the installment plan, over a long period
of time. So therefore it will not you know as opposed to...
So it's לאו באיי ישלח יד. Lav b'ei yishlach yad. I don't
want to send my hand against you, the Jewish people, to punish
you all at once. That would be too destructive, I leave that
for the other nations. You, it's בפידו B'pido like a little pecking,
and שוע Shoa it'll be salvation for you to have a little
bit you know to distribute your punishment over time. Okay, דבר אחר,
Davar acher,
another explanation, אפילו אין ישראל עושים מצוה לפני כי אם מעט כפיד
של תרנגולים. Afilu ein Yisrael osim mitzvah lifanai ki im me'at k'pid
shel tarnegolim.
Even if the Jewish people only do before me מצוות a little
bit, like the pecking of a chicken שמנקרין באשפה Shemenakrin b'ashpah that
they peck in the in the garbage dunk, the garbage heap, אני
מצרפן לחשבון גדול, Ani metzarfan l'cheshbon gadol, I'll add it all up
to a big thing. שנאמר אם בפידו להן שוע. Im b'pido lahen
shoa. דבר אחר, Davar acher, בזכות שמשוועים לפני, Bizchut shemeshva'im lifanai,
in the merit that they cry out to me you know, I
meaning it means because of their anguish, because of the way they're
being oppressed, you know, does it mean that they pray to me?
Presumably the anguish. אני מושיע אותם, Ani moshia otam, I will save
them. והיינו דאמר רבי אבא, V'hainu d'amar Rabbi Abba, מאי דכתיב, mai
d'ketiv what's meant by the verse, ואנכי אפדם והמה דברו עלי כזבים.
V'anochi efdem vehama dibru alai kezavim. I will redeem them and they
have spoken on me falsehoods. אני אמרתי אפדם בממונם בעולם הזה. Ani
amarti efdem bemamonam b'olam hazeh. And
I said and I will sort of you know redeem the Jewish
people, meaning so I will take by my payments from them, you
know, punishment for their sin will be the fact that they suffer
a little bit in this world. Okay, so that's how God is
going to redeem us, he'll bring our you know this is the
classic rabbinic trope, why
do the non-Jews have it good and the Jews have it bad?
Because God is paying up the Jews for their sins in this
world so we'll be rewarded in the world to come, and he's
paying the non-Jews up for their מצוות and their good deeds in
this world so that they won't get the merit in the world
to come. You know of course the problem with all of this
is as opposed to before where the I mean you know besides
the general problem being that it doesn't you know some passages in
the גמרא Gemara don't conform to people's contemporary more pluralistic you know
universalistic ethos, but besides that before it was basically saying like you
know the Jews did the right thing and the non-Jews did the
wrong thing, of course it was very generalized. choosing to look at
all non-Jews in one brush and all Jews in another brush, but
anyway, but at least it was just at least what it was
describing was fair, you know, in the sense that you guys have
had your chance, you didn't do the שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva
mitzvot b'nei Noach, you guys did the תרי"ג מצוות, taryag mitzvot, right,
that's sort of the way it was presented. Here it's a little
bit like, it's not fair. Why does God choose to punish, you
know, the non-Jews one way and the Jews another way? Why does
God, you know, there's clearly like the process is not fair, not
just, you know, the outcome is different. Okay. So, but you know,
but that maybe the answer, you know, that's sort of the general
sense, maybe the answer because we have a covenant with God, is
the answer because we've merited this because in general our actions, you
know, are seen to be better, like, you know, but anyway here
this sense of favoritism, more, you know, is much more stands out
than in the earlier discussion. Okay.
Okay. אני אמרתי אשלם בנם ולמזק ani amarti ashlam banam v'limidzak כדי
שיזכו kedai sheyizku עולם הבא olam haba they would merit in the
world to come, והם דברו עלי כזבים v'heim dibru alai k'zavim but
these ingrates, the Jewish people, you know, they spoke falsehood about me,
they complained and said why is God punishing us? And they didn't
realize that I was doing this ultimately to reward you. והיינו דאמר
רב פפי v'hainu d'amar Rav Papi that's what רב פפי Rav Papi
says משמיה דרבא mishmei d'Rava מאי דכתיב d'ksiv, what's meant by the
verse ואני יסרתי חזקתי זרועתם va'ani yasarti chizakti z'ro'otam I brought out,
you know, I sort of
afflicted them, I strengthened their arms, ואלי יחשבו רע v'elai yachsh'vu ra
and they considered it to be bad and they thought evil against
me. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu אני אמרתי איסרם
ביסורין בעולם הזה ani amarti ayasrim b'yisurin ba'olam hazeh I thought that
I would afflict them in this world כדי שיחזקו זרועתם לעולם הבא
kedai sheyechazku z'ro'otam l'olam haba to strengthen their, you know, their power,
their arms in the world to come. It's like, you know, when
somebody makes you do a hard workout and go to the gym,
right? You curse them under your breath, but at the end of
the day, you know, it's good for you, right? Because they're, it's
strengthening you and it's helping your health. ואלי יחשבו רע v'elai yachsh'vu
ra and so all they did is they cursed me under their
breath, you know, they say they attributed evil to me. Okay, משתבח
mistabeach fine. So that's sort of the end, God sort of does
this all for our benefit. We should take consolation, you know, it's
interesting, I happened to see like I mentioned in the past that
with all of the wonderful new translations out in Artscroll and all
of that, Soncino, okay, it's a little stilted translation Soncino, it's a
much more literal one, but anyway, but it has good scholarly notes
which I've been very disappointed that even like the שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz גמרא
Gemara which has all these wonderful pictures on the side or whatever,
sometimes it doesn't have some of the relevant scholarship about some of
this stuff. So anyway, one of the interesting things it sort of
said at a footnote right at the beginning, you know, all these
דרשות drashot here at the beginning, you know, I've been sort of
talking about how it's there to frame how do we look at
the larger world, or that's implicitly the message, but they also point
out, you know, that it's about bringing consolation, you know, that one
of the points of a דרשה drasha was to speak to an
oppressed people who are having, who are suffering, and you know, whatever,
and trying to explain to them it'll all be okay in the
future. And here's how to understand why you're suffering and they have
it good. You know, so that's like a theme, right, it opens
up in the future time, you know, they're going to try to
justify themselves, but you know, that's their, God's going to mock them,
you're going to be rewarded. You know, especially if you talk about
יום אידם, Yom Edam, which is the opening משנה, Mishna, right, which
is both their holidays. So here he is, you know, you're in
this pagan culture and everybody's celebrating all of these pagan holidays, right,
and you're sort of wondering like what the heck am I, you
know, like they're obviously the successful ones, you know, and like this
is the, so and you know and turning it and saying no
ultimately that יום איד, Yom Ed, that holiday will be יום אידם
Yom Edam will be their downfall. Right, so but so part of
the message here is, is also like a consolation of what does
it mean to be a tiny oppressed minority in this larger, you
know, sort of culture and sort of saying in the end you'll
all be rewarded. So seeing it through that lens. So anyway, the
interesting point that there was made in that footnote was that if
you think about the קדיש דרבנן, Kaddish DeRabbanan, right, that we, that
was said after a דרשה, drasha, which we still say, the קדיש
דרבנן Kaddish DeRabbanan says, you know, לעילא לעילא מכל שירתא ותשבחתא ונחמתא.
l'eila l'eila mikol shirata v'tushbechata v'nechemata. God is praised above all of
the, all of the songs and the praises and the נחמה, nechama,
the consolations. Why's the word consolation doing in a קדיש Kaddish that's
about learning תורה? So the point was, was that these types of
דרשות drashot were called נחמתא, nechamata, they were to give consolation to
like an oppressed people, you know, so anyway, so so that's I
think clearly this, these last themes here. Okay, so now moving on.
משתבח הוה רבי אבהו, Mistabeach havah Rabbi Abahu, רבי אבהו Rabbi Abahu
was praised למיני l'minei to a certain heretic, again, does that mean
a Jewish Christian? Who does that mean exactly? ברב ספרא, B'Rav Safra,
about רב ספרא. Rav Safra. דאדם גדול הוא, d'adam gadol hu, oh
my God, you should hear about רב ספרא, Rav Safra, what a
huge תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. All right, so שבקו ליה מכסא דתלת
עסרי שנין, shavku lei michsa d'tlat esrei shanin, so this מין, min,
this heretic or whatever this Jewish Christian apparently he was a government
official and he therefore what he did was that he basically gave
him a pass on, on the, on tax for, for thirteen years,
so you know, we, you know, so talk about like tax breaks,
you know? So anyway, he got a thirteen year, you know, pass
on the tax break. Doesn't mean that he had owed thirteen years
of back taxes and he just forgot about it, he waived it.
Okay, anyway, that's what it sounds like. Anyway, יומא חד אשכחוה, yoma
chad ashk'chuh, one day this מין min bumped into to רבי אבהו,
Rabbi Abahu, or to רב ספרא. Rav Safra. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he says to him, oh, I've heard about you, let me ask
you something. כתיב, Ktiv, one verse says... רק אתכם ידעתי מכל משפחות
האדמה על כן אפקוד עליכם את כל עונותיכם, Rak etchem yadati mikol
mishpechot haadama al ken efkod aleichem et kol avonoteichem, only you I
know from all of the families of the land, therefore I visit
upon you all your sins. And ידעתי yadati sort of means like
I loved you, I've chosen you. So מאן דאית ליה סניא ברחמי
מסיק ליה? man deit lei sanya berachamei masik lei? So somebody who
has anger, does he direct it against his loved ones? Because I
loved you, I visited your sins upon you. What the heck does
that mean? אישתיק, Ishtik, he was silenced. לא הוה בידיה למימר ליה
ולא מידי. Lo hava beyadei lemeimar lei velo midi. He couldn't respond,
he didn't have a good
answer. רמו ליה סודרא בצוואריה. Ramu lei sudra betzavarei. So basically then,
what, and you're supposed to be this big תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham?
So they basically threw him into handcuffs,
which here is that they put a handkerchief around his neck to
drag him off into jail or whatever to afflict him, וקא מצערו
ליה, veka mitzaaru lei, and they were afflicting
him. So, here you were, I waived your taxes and you don't
know anything. So אתא רבי אבהו, Ata Rabbi Abbahu, Rabbi Abbahu came,
אשכחינהו, ashkechinhu, he found them what was happening. אמר להו, Amar lehu,
he said, אמאי מצעריתו ליה? amai mitzaaritu lei? Why are you afflicting
him? אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him, דלאו אמרת לן
דאדם גדול הוא? delav amart lan de'adam gadol hu? What do you
mean? You told us he was a great תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and we were nice to him as a result and he clearly
he's not. ולא ידע למימר לן פירושא דהאי פסוקא, Velo yada lemeimar
lan perusha dehai pasuka, and he couldn't even give us a good
explanation of this verse. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them,
אימא דאמרי לכו בתנאי. eima de'amri lachon betana'ei. When did I tell
you that he was a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham when it
came to rabbinic literature? בקראי מי אמרי לכו? Bekra'ei mi amri lachon?
I never said that he knew how to explain biblical verses. So
funny like even at the time of the rabbis, they understood the
phenomenon of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham who knows all of ש"ס
Shas but doesn't know what a
פסוק. pasuk. So the רש"ש, Rashash, one of the more recent commentator
on the גמרא, Gemara, in the beginning of the גמרא Gemara in
בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, it talks about how during years of famine,
רבי Rebbi basically had all these warehouses and he said I'm only
going to provide food for somebody who's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
not the עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz don't get food. So somebody who
wanted to show רבי Rebbi, that it was not proper to do
that, a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, anyway he dressed up and
he pretended
that he was an עם הארץ am ha'aretz and he came to
רבי Rebbi and he said, רבי, Rebbi feed me. And רבי said,
have you learned תנ"ך? Tanakh? And he said no. He says, have
you learned משנה? Mishna? And he said no. Anyway, so the רש"ש
Rashash interrupts the narrative and says, ah, you see that even after
he said he didn't learn תנ"ך, Tanakh, רבי thought it was possible
that he still had learned the rabbinic literature. So this shows you
that it's possible to know rabbinic literature without knowing תנ"ך. Tanakh. היכא
דלהוי. Heicha delihavei. But anyway, but that was a common phenomenon. Anyway,
so this is what he is saying to him. Okay, he knows
the rabbinic literature, he doesn't know תנ"ך. Tanakh. אמרו ליה, Amru lei,
מאי שנא אתון דידעיתון? mai shena atun deyad'itun? So if that's true,
how come you, Rabbi Abbahu, how come you know תנ"ך Tanakh if
what the rabbinic culture is about learning the rabbinic literature and it
doesn't include learning תנ"ך? Tanakh? How do you get to be that
you're such a בקי baki in תנ"ך? Tanakh? Because we know those
are the conversations we have with you all the time. So אמר
להו, Amar lehu, he said to them, אנן דשכיחן גבייכון, anan deshachichan
gabayichun,
we that are found among you, like we regularly have these types
of discourses with you about תנ"ך, Tanakh, about פסוקים. pesukim. This makes
it sound very much that we're talking about Jewish Christians and about
that's what it means by מין. min. And that therefore they would
always, we know this in the Middle Ages, right? So much of
the Jewish Christian debate were about trying to
prove who is right based on the biblical verses that we both
shared, right? Based on arguing based on the Jewish scriptures, Christians were
trying to prove you see that Christianity ultimately was foretold. And all
of those disputations would a lot be around the תנ"ך. Tanakh. So
basically, so it seems like that's the context and that Rabbi Abbahu
was a constant, there's other indications about this, that there were these
sort of arenas in which settings in which they would debate these
verses of תנ"ך. Tanakh. So that's what he says. He says, look,
we are among you and this is a common discourse that we
Jews have with you מינים. minim. So therefore רמינן אנפשין ומעיינן, raminan
anafshin ume'aynan, we make a point of learning תנ"ך Tanakh better so
we'll know how to respond to your claims.
אינהו לא מעייני. Inhu lo me'aynei. But those that stay cloistered up
in the ישיבה, yeshiva, they don't know תנ"ך. Tanakh. Okay. But by
the way, you understand also the point about them quoting a verse
about you being an afflicted people, right? Because do you look at
the afflictions of the Jews as a sign, right? The classic Christian
theology is that it's because that the Jews didn't accept Jesus and
that's why the Jews are the afflicted people, right? So and here's
a verse that says, no,
we're afflicted because God loves us. So he sort of, so that's
why that would sort of be the verse that was being challenged,
right? So אמרו ליה, Amru lei, לימא לן את, leima lan at,
they said, okay, fine. So you tell us. How would you read
this verse? אמר להו, Amar lehu, what does it mean God says
because I loved you I afflict? אמר להו, Amar lehu, he says
to them, אמשול לכם משל, emshol lachem mashal, let me give you
an example. למה הדבר דומה? Lema hadavar domeh? What is this like?
Not an example, a parable. לאדם שנושה משני... le'adam shenosheh mishnei... משני
בני
אדם *mishnei bnei adam*. Person has borrowed money from two people. בני
אדם *bnei adam*, אחד אוהבו *echad ohavo*, one is his person who's
his who's his friend, who's very, you know, who loves him, ואחד
שונאו *ve'echad sono*, one who hates him. אוהבו נפרע ממנו מעט מעט
*ohavo nifra mimeno me'at me'at*, the one who loves him goes on
the installment plan. He allows him to pay off $10 a week
until it's all paid off. שונאו נפרע ממנו בבת אחת *sono nifra
mimeno b'vas achas*, the one who hates him waits a few months
and then comes and demands all $10,000 at once. Okay, so that's
why God says because I loved you, I will visit your sins
upon you means that you will regularly you will suffer a little
by a little and a little at a time so you don't
have to suffer all big and all at once. אמר רבי אבא
בר כהנא *amar Rabbi Abba Bar Kahana*: מאי דכתיב *mai dechsiv*, what's
meant by the verse חלילה לך מעשות כדבר הזה *chalila lecha me'asot
kadavar hazeh*, God forbid for you to do such things. This is
Avraham arguing with God about Sdom. להמית צדיק עם רשע *lehamis tzaddik
im rasha*, to kill a righteous with a wicked. אמר אברהם לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar Avraham lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu*: רבונו של עולם
*Ribono Shel Olam*, Master of the Universe, חולין הוא מעשות כדבר הזה
*chulin hu me'asot kadavar hazeh*. It is considered it's profane for you
to act in this way, להמית צדיק עם רשע *lehamis tzaddik im
rasha*. But hello, but is that really true? Like now we're going
to question because a lot of this is about right the justice
in the future time, the Messianic times, and why do we suffer
in this world? So now we're actually start asking some questions about
that. Is that really true that God doesn't bring the death of
the righteous together with the wicked? והכתיב והכרתי ממך צדיק ורשע *vehachsiv
vehichrasti mimcha tzaddik verasha*, I will cut off from you the righteous
and the wicked. בצדיק שאינו גמור *betzaddik she'eino gamur*. That's not somebody
who's truly righteous. אבל בצדיק גמור לא *aval betzaddik gamur lo*? Are
you telling me that somebody who's truly righteous that they won't suffer
that fate? וכתיב וממקדשי תחלו *ve'achsiv umimikdashi tichalu*, and from my sanctuary
you shall begin the destruction. ותני רב יוסף *vetani Rav Yosef*, and
Rav Yosef taught: אל תקרי ממקדשי *al tikri mimikdashi*, don't read from
my sanctuary, אלא ממקודשי *ela mimikudashai*, from those that are sanctified by
me. אלו בני אדם שקיימו את כל התורה מאלף ועד תיו *elu
bnei adam shekiymu es kol hatorah me'alef ve'ad taf*, the human beings
that have fulfilled the entire Torah from A to Z, and they
are the ones who will first be afflicted when the time of,
you know, affliction or destruction comes. התם נמי *hasam nami*, there too,
כיון שהיה בידם למחות ולא מיחו *kivan she'haya beyadam limchos velo michu*,
since they could have protested to the wicked that was being done
in the world and they did not, הוו להו כצדיקים שאינם גמורים
*havu lehu ketzaddikim she'einam gmurim*. They are the righteous they are not
fully righteous. Don't tell me that you're fully righteous because of your
own personal deeds, if you, you know, don't be a silent enabler,
right? And a lot of that is, you know, current also like
in the whole MeToo and coming to the surface, but it's always
an issue, right? Who is the one that said all the wicked
all wicked needs to succeed is for good men to stay silent
and do nothing? Or something like that and say nothing? Right? So
the silent enablers are a major part of what allows evil to
succeed. So don't tell me you're righteous just because your deeds are
righteous.
Okay, so now partly though again within the larger context presumably what
it's doing is trying to explain to people why it is that
it looks like good people suffer. So one explanation is well God
is paying off a little bit at a time. But there's still
people who say no, no, no, it's unjust, you know, and God
says no, it is just. If people are suffering then there's a
reason that they're suffering. They're not totally righteous. Okay. רב פפא רמי
*Rav Papa rami*: כתיב *kesiv*, it says, אל זועם בכל יום El
zo'em bechol yom. *El zo'em bechol yom*, God gets angry every day.
וכתיב *vechesiv*, and it says, לפני זעמו מי יעמוד Lifnei zaamo mi
ya'amod. *lifnei za'amo mi ya'amod*, who can stand before God's anger? So
if God gets angry every day and God's anger, you know, will
just, you know, nobody can survive, so why isn't the world destroyed?
לא קשיא *lo kashya*, it's not difficult. כאן ביחיד beyachid, כאן בציבור
*kan beyachid kan betzibur*. It does an individual can't stand in front
of God's anger. But when God like judges the entire world, the
merit of the entire world prevents God's anger from, you know, destroying
it. Now again that sort of theme that like the world is
deserving of destruction but it's preserved. Okay. תנו רבנן *tanu Rabbanan*: אל
זועם בכל יום El zo'em bechol yom, *El zo'em bechol yom*, God
gets angry every day. וכמה זעמו V'chama zaamo? *vekamah za'amo*, how long
is God's wrath, I shouldn't just say anger, anger is a little
tame word, God's wrathful every day. And how long is his wrath?
רגע Rega. *rega*, an instant. וכמה רגע V'chama rega? *vekamah rega*, how
long does an instant last? אחת מחמש ריבוא ושלשת אלפים ושמונה מאות
וארבעים ושמונה בשעה *achas michamesh ribo ushloshes alafim ushmonah me'os ve'arba'im ushmonah
besha'ah*. One
53,848th of an hour. I have no idea where they got that.
But if we round up to 60,000 because of an hour, so
you drop the 60, so it's 1/1,000th of a minute. So what
is that? Anyway, you divide it by another 60, so it's one
I guess one like less than like 1/150th of a second. Okay.
זו היא רגע rega. *zo hi rega*. This is a רגע rega?
*rega*. ואין כל בריה יכולה לכוין אותה רגע rega. *ve'ein kol biryah
yecholah lechaven osah rega*, and no human being can creature can identify
that instant that 1/1,000th of a second that God is angry. חוץ
מבלעם הרשע *chutz miBilam harasha*, except for Bilam the wicked. דכתיב ביה
*dechsiv beih*, because it says by Bilam, יודע דעת עליון *yode'a da'as
Elyon*, he who knows the thought of the Most High. So this
is like such a wonderful גמרא Gemara *Gemara* like puncturing like Bilam's
arrogance. אפשר דעת בהמתו לא הוה ידע *efshar da'as behemto lo hava
yada*, he couldn't even know what his animal was thinking. דעת עליון
מי הוה ידע *da'as Elyon mi hava yada*, could he know what
God was thinking? So מאי דעת בהמתו לא הוה יודע? What does
it mean he couldn't know what his animal was thinking? בעידנא דחזו
ליה דהוה רכיב חמריה. Be'idna dechazu lei dehavah rachiv chamarei. So when
you know it says בלעם Bilam goes and he saddles up his
donkey, you know, to go with the שרי מדין Sarei Midyan or
whatever מואב. Moav. So it says that when they saw him saddling
up his donkey, so אמרו ליה, Amru lei, they said to him,
מאי טעמא לא רכבת סוסיא? Mai taama lo rachavta susaya? Why are
you riding on a donkey? You should ride on a horse. That's
a more honorable type of a ride. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he
said to them, בירטיבא שדיא. Be'irtiva shadya. Yeah, it's over in the...
it's grazing in the swamp. It wasn't available, my horse. שדי ליה.
Shadi lei. מיד, immediately, ותאמר האתון, Vatomer ha'ason, the donkey answered back,
הלא אנכי אתונך. Halo anochi asonecha. What do you mean? It's not
like you usually use a horse and נעבעך nebach you had to
use me. I am your donkey. I'm the one you always ride
on. אמר לה, Amar lah, לטעינא בעלמא. L'teina b'alma. No, I just
used you for a beast of burden. I don't ride on you.
אמרה ליה, Amra lei, אשר רכבת עלי. Asher rachavta alai. No, I
am the donkey that you always ride on. אמר לה, Amar lah,
אקראי בעלמא. Akrai b'alma. Yeah, occasionally. אמרה ליה, Amra lei, the donkey
said back, מעודך ועד היום הזה. Me'odecha ve'ad hayom hazeh. No, you
know, from your entire life, I am your regular ride. ולא עוד
אלא, V'lo od ela, and now we get to understand why does
he choose to ride on a donkey, שאני עושה לך רכיבה ביום,
She'ani osa lecha rechiva bayom, I provide you ride during the day,
I ride for you in the day, ואישות בלילה, V'ishus balaila, and
I act to you as a wife at night. Okay, so obviously
this is completely like mocking בלעם. Bilam. כתיב הכא, Kasiv hacha, how
do you know, ההסכן הסכנתי לעשות לך כה. Hahasken hiskanti la'asos lecha
koh. Have I ever like sort of you know risked or whatever?
Have I ever you know done this type of... something like this
to you? That's what the donkey says to בלעם. Bilam. But we'll
look at the word הסכן. hasken. So what does הסכן hasken mean?
וכתיב התם ותהי לו סוכנת. Uchasiv hasam vatehi lo sochenes. It says
by דוד, David, you know, by the אבישג השונמית, Avishag Hashunamis, that
she was a warmer for him, like he slept together with her,
with him, you know, to provide warmth. In the verse there by
דוד. David. So anyway, so you see he says that I am
your... I'm like your wife. So anyway, so he didn't even know
what his donkey was thinking. I mean I you know not only
could he not read his donkey's mind, but he couldn't even best
his donkey in an argument. אלא מאי יודע דעת
עליון? Ela mai yodeia daas elyon? Such a fool! What does it
mean he knows the thought of the Most High? אלא שהיה יודע
כיוון אותה שעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא כועס בה. Ela shehaya yodeia kivein
osah sha'ah shehakadosh baruch hu ko'es bah.
He knew that exact instant when God got wrathful against the world,
and therefore he was able to pinpoint it and he therefore if
he sort of you know prayed to God at that moment or
tapped into that anger, he could bring terrible destruction.
והיינו דקאמר להו נביא, V'hainu dekamar lehu navi, and that's what the
נביא Navi says to ישראל, Yisrael, עמי זכור נא מה יעץ בלק
מלך מואב. Ami zechor na mah ya'atz Balak melech Moav. Remember what
בלק Balak the king of מואב Moav planned against you. ומה ענה
אותו בלעם בן בעור, Umah ana oso Bilam ben Be'or, how בלעם
Bilam responded to him, מן השטים עד הגלגל, Min Hashittim ad haGilgal,
from the שטים Shittim to the גלגל Gilgal when you were encamped
in that place. למען דעת צדקות ה'. Lema'an daas sidkos Hashem. You
should know the righteousness of God. So what are we supposed to
know? What are we supposed to understand about that event that tells
us the righteousness of God? So you would say, well you know
God you know changed the curses into blessings and so on. But
here it says, אמר רבי אלעזר אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל,
Amar Rabbi Elazar amar lahem Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, God says to
the Jewish people, עמי ראו כמה צדקות עשיתי עמכם. Ami reu kama
tzedakos asisi imachem.
You should know how much acts of righteousness I did with you
at that time. שלא כעסתי עליכם. Shelo kaas'ti aleichem. I held back
that instant of wrath that I have every day. כל אותן הימים.
Kol osan hayamim. שלא כעסתי עליכם כל אותן הימים. Shelo kaas'ti aleichem
kol osan hayamim.
Had I allowed myself to have that instant of wrath, לא נשתייר
משונאיהם של ישראל שריד ופליט. Lo nishtayer mishoneihem shel Yisrael sarid ufalit.
So it would not have been left from the haters, from the
non-Jewish haters of Israel any remnant. Right? That's just a way of...
you know they don't want to say that the Jews would be
destroyed. So it says, you know, so it sort of displaces it.
But I mean nobody of the Jewish people would have been destroyed
if I had allowed myself to get angry, בלעם Bilam would have
tapped into that moment of anger. והיינו דקאמר ליה בלעם לבלק, V'hainu
dekamar lei Bilam l'Balak, and that's what בלעם Bilam says to בלק,
Balak, מה אקב לא קבה אל. Mah ekov lo kaboh El. How...
what will I curse that God has not cursed? ומה אזעום, Umah
ezom, and here's the tie to the word זעם, zaam, right? לפני
זעמו מי יעמוד. Lifnei zaamo mi ya'amod, אל זועם בכל יום. E-l
zo'eim b'chol yom,
It's a brilliant אגדתא, right? לפני זעמו מי יעמוד,
nobody can withstand God's wrath. You know, אל זועם בכל יום, there's
that moment of wrath in the day. And בלעם Bilam was going
to try to tap into that moment of wrath, and here we
have זעום zaam used in the third פסוק, pasuk, right? Where it
says מה אזעום לא זעם ה'. Mah ezom lo zaam Hashem.
What can I bring wrath against that God has not shown wrath?
So as... so therefore the... so therefore
God has chosen to not... to withhold that moment of wrath, and
therefore I cannot tap into it and I cannot bring destruction. וכמה
זעמו? And how long is that moment of wrath? רגע. rega, A
רגע. rega. וכמה רגע? rega How long is a רגע? rega. So
we just said it's like one one-hundredth of a second. But now
we're going to say, אמר אמימר ואיתימא רבינא רגע כמימריה. Amar Amemar
v'isema Ravina rega kemimrei. It's as long as it takes you to
say the word
רגע. That's it. Okay? ומנלן דרגע הוי רתיחה. Umanalan derega havei resicha.
associate, excuse me, the רגע, the moment, right, with the idea of
God's wrath? Because the other verse said א-ל זועם בכל יום, every
day. But now we're limiting the time of the anger, of the
wrath, to a רגע. Where's that association of רגע with God's anger?
דכתיב, because the verse says, כי רגע באפו חיים ברצונו, ki rega
b'apo chayim birtzono, only a moment in God's
anger, a lifetime in God's favor. אי בעית אימא מהכא, ee bayis
eima mehacha, if you want, you could say from here, חבי כמעט
רגע עד יעבור זעם, chavi khimat rega ad ya'avor za'am, wait a
moment until the wrath passes. There you have, that's actually a better
verse because it has the word זעם za'am again. Okay. Okay, now,
so that, what?
Isn't that related to when the non-Jewish kings get up and pray
in the morning?
Yeah, we're going to tie that... we're going to get there, it's
coming up. Okay. By the way, there's a very... two תוספות. Tosafos.
If you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says, רגע כמימריה. rega
k'memrei. תוספות Tosafos says, ואי תימא מאי יכיל למימר בההיא שעתא דפורתא
כולי האי, v'ee tima mai yachil l'meimar b'hahi sha'ata d'purta kuli hai,
what could Bileam have said, even if he knew that exact second?
You know, what can you say in a... in a... in a,
you know, in a half a second to, you know, to... to...
you know, if you only have that tiny window? So, ויש לומר
היה אומר
כלם, v'yeish lomar hayah omer kaleim, destroy them. ויש לומר היה אומר
כלם. v'yeish lomar hayah omer kaleim. I guess you could say that
in as long as it takes to say רגע. והקדוש ברוך הוא
הפכו ואמר מלך דכתיב ותרועת מלך בו. v'Hakadosh Baruch Hu hafcho v'amar
melech d'chsiv v'sruas melech bo. And God reversed it and rather than
כלם, kaleim, the word the reverse is מלך, melech, דכתיב ותרועת מלך
בו. d'chsiv v'sruas melech bo. So that's one answer. You could just
say one word: כלם. kaleim. רבי אליהו היה מפרש דאין צריך להכניס
כל הקללה באותו רגע. Rabbi Eliyahu hayah mefareish d'ein tzarich l'hachnis kol
haklalah b'oso rega. You only have to begin, you have to start,
tap into that. Once you got in that little opening and you
began your prayer, then, דכיון דאתחלת באותו רגע תדע שהיה רוצה להאריך
בקללה וכו' כדפירש בקונטרס וכו'. d'keivan d'as-chalt b'oso rega teida shehayah rotzeh
l'ha'arich b'klalah v'chu k'difreish b'kuntres v'chu. Okay, so anyway, so all you
have to do is get into that opening and then he could
have spent his time and it all would have tapped into that
anger. There's interesting, you know, the רגאטשובר, Rogatchover, you know, was, you
know, this brilliant Rabbi from about 100 years ago. He was like
this very out-of-the-box thinker, like he would make these weird comparisons. Anyway,
so the question was, like, if somebody starts דאווענינג, davening, right, you
know, a minute before the end of the זמן, zman, does it
count דאווענינג davening in the זמן? zman? You know, like, if it's
a minute before, you know, whatever, the end of חצות Chatzos or
before sunset or whatever the case might be, does it count like
he's דאווענט davened in the... during the זמן zman or not? So
he, based on this תוספות, Tosafos, you see it only matters that
you started at the right time.
Yeah, so exactly.
Anyway, alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
ואימת רתח? v'eimas rasach?
So now, we said only בלעם Bileam knew that, but you know,
let's us try to get at least a rough sense of when
is that moment of God's anger. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, בתלת
שעי קמייתא כי חיוורא כרבלתא דתרנגולא, b'slas sha'ei kmaisa ki chivra karbalta
d'sarnagola, the first three hours of the day, when the crown of
the rooster is white. So the גמרא Gemara says, כל שעתא ושעתא
מחורא כרבלתא. kol sha'ata v'sha'ata machvara karbalta. So the גמרא Gemara says,
no, every... what do you mean? Every... the crown of a rooster
is always white. No, כל שעתא אית ביה סריקי סומקי. kol sha'ata
is beih serikei sumkei. No, normally there are like red streaks in
it. ההיא שעתא, hahi sha'ata, at that one second, לית ביה סריקי
סומקי, leis beih serikei sumkei, you'll only see pure white, no red
streaks. So now, based on this, now we have a way of
identifying that moment. רבי יהושע בן לוי הוה מצער ליה ההוא מינא.
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi havah m'tza'ar lei hahu mina. Back to the
מין. min. There was a certain מין min that was giving רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi a hard time, בקראי. bikrai.
Now, if you interest... if you insert in the brackets, it doesn't
mean he was giving him a physically afflicting him. It means like
the theme we mentioned before: he was quoting... he was quoting verses,
biblical verses, to try to demonstrate the rightness of his faith and
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi was having a hard
time responding. Okay, he was losing those types of disputations. יומא חד
נקט תרנגולא. yoma chad nakat tarnagola. So what was he going to
do? So one day he took a rooster. ואוקמיה בין כרעי דערסא.
v'okmei bein karei d'arsa. He put it between the legs of his
bed. ועיין בה. v'ayein bah. And he focused on it. סבר כי
מטי ההיא שעתא אלטייה. savar ki mati hahi sha'ata alteiyeh. I'm going
to keep my eyes on this for three straight hours and when,
you know, I see that it turns white, then I'll curse this
מין min and he'll be... and to get him off my back.
כי מטי ההיא שעתא נים. ki mati hahi sha'ata num. When that
moment came, he had fallen asleep. Okay. There's like... I don't know
if anybody ever read Kafka's 'The Castle'. Oh my God, that was
such a long book. It was so hard to get through. But
anyway, but the end of it, like, there's this guy... it's basically,
it's all some obviously Kafkaesque story. Anyway, about like presumably trying to
find the true meaning of life or whatever it is. Anyway, so
this guy is looking and looking the whole book, he's trying to
understand like, you know, why this person is here in this town
or whatever. Anyway, at the very end of the book, he finally
finds somebody who says, 'I will tell you like what, you know,
you know, what we're doing here.' And then at the... and then
at the critical moment, the guy falls asleep, right when it's time
for him to finally be told what it is, you know, the...
you know, what it's all about. So anyway, so alright. At that
critical moment he fell asleep. אמר... Like Yitzchak and Esav when he's
going to give him the blessing. Yeah, that's God removes it, but
there's something a little bit funnier about like... about you spending like,
whatever, 500-page book like, you know, trying to find... you're spending your
life trying to... so we... So we actually had the ישיבה yeshiva
recently Biti Roi, who’s a wonderful, you know, teacher. She teaches קבלה
Kabbalah and חסידות. Chasidus. Anyway, so she told the story about, I
think it was רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. I don’t remember if it
was רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. Anyway, you know, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman,
I think it might have been רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, or she
might have quoted somebody else. Anyway, who said, you know, the whole
question about how can there be, you know, divine foreknowledge and free
choice, right? The quest that, like, involved, you know, philosophers, you know,
have spent, like, you know, whatever, all this time trying to understand.
So there’s a story that רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, yeah, you
know, when I was young I figured out the answer to that,
and I wrote the answer on a piece of paper, and, yeah,
I lost it. So which is like, so it's like a message
about, like, you know, is it really about the answer or is
it really like, you know, or is it really about, anyway, you
could read that a couple of ways. Is it about searching for
the answer? Is it about the answer? Is any answer really the
true answer? Anyway, so it’s all the same. Okay, yes, at that
moment he fell asleep. אמר שמע מינה, Amar shema mina, so you
see from this: לאו אורח ארעא למעבד הכי. lav orach ara lemeevad
hachi. It’s not the right thing to do. You know, even though
this could get him off my back, you know, you don't act
this way. It's not the right way for a righteous person to
act. ורחמיו על כל מעשיו כתיב. Verachamav al kol maasav kesiv. God’s
compassion is on all God’s creatures. We shouldn't wish evil on anyone,
even the people that are afflicting us. וכתיב גם ענוש לצדיק לא
טוב. Ukesiv gam anosh latzaddik lo tov. Even punishment, but here the
bringing of punishment is not appropriate for a righteous person. תנא משמיה
דרבי מאיר. Tana mishmeih de-Rabbi Meir. We tell in the name of
Rabbi Meir. There’s a Christian element here, do you think? What do
you mean? I mean, like, it seems that in judgment it’s appropriate
in terms of supporting the idea of what’s right and wrong that
there will be punishment. Oh, like turn the other cheek? Yeah, right.
Maybe, but I’m not so sure that, yeah, I hear that. I
just think it means that, you know, it’s the turn the other
cheek is a little bit of an extreme because it's almost to
the point of don’t even defend yourself, you know, as opposed to
there’s a little difference between just expose yourself to being beaten up
and don’t defend yourself as opposed to, you know, you shouldn't be
going ahead and attacking other people. So I, maybe, but I read
this more as like a righteous person doesn’t go and attack people,
even people like he, I think just attacking and bringing punishment on
people is different than defending yourself. God brings punishment. Are we supposed
to be the agents of bringing punishment on other people? Yeah, Psalm
149, I think at the end, doesn’t it say the righteous will
do this to the wicked? Yeah, I mean, I’m not saying those
things are, I mean, absent from our tradition, but the question is,
you know, the message here is not that. Okay, isn’t that a
conflict with what we did a couple minutes ago about if you
just are silent and enable evil, you’re not a צדיק גמור? tzaddik
gamur? So here you mean, right, but this is not about evil
in the world, you mean. So how are you saying it, that
like by that if you see a bad guy, are you supposed
to, oh, are you supposed to attack him? And attack him, right,
right. So I think that’s an interesting question. I think here the
point is fundamentally you’re not there to stop evil being done, you’re
trying to just protect yourself, you know? I think that there’s a
difference, like, you know, you're trying, you know, somebody’s afflicting you and
you want to punish that person, there's something much more personal and
less righteous about that type of an activity than when somebody is
doing evil out in the world. Also there’s a question, right, about
punishing as opposed to stopping the activity. Before the גמרא Gemara spoke
about מיחה, mecha, like to protest, you know? And I think that's
different than a desire to see punishment brought, right? You know, because
that does tap into our lower, you know, yes, you could sort
of do it from a high-minded place, but like to want to
get vengeance, right, that does tap into our, like, you know, our
more base instincts. Okay, anyway, so, okay. תנא משמיה דרבי מאיר. Tana
mishmeih de-Rabbi Meir. We tell in the name of Rabbi Meir.
בשעה שמלכים מניחים כתריהם בראשיהם ומשתחווים לחמה.
Beshaah shemelachim
manichim kisreihem berosheihem umishtachavim lachamah. When they put their, you know, when
the kings, like, take their crowns off and bow down to the
sun, you know, they sort of show their mortality and, you know,
their humanness, and they put their crowns aside, but what they worship
is the sun. מיד כועס הקדוש ברוך הוא. Miyad koes HaKadosh Baruch
Hu. God immediately gets angry. אמר רב יוסף. Amar Rav Yosef. So
that’s that moment of anger of the, maybe, it’s not clear if
it’s directly connecting it to the previous point about the זעם. zaam.
אמר רב יוסף לא ליצלי איניש צלותא דמוספי בתלת שעי קמייתא דיומא
קמא דראש השנה ביחיד. Amar Rav Yosef lo litzli inish tzluta demusaffi
betlas sha'ei kamaisa deyoma kama deRosh Hashanah beyachid. Do not pray מוסף
Musaf during the first three hours of the day on the first
day of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah ביחיד, when you’re alone, when you’re
not in the ציבור. tzibbur. Why? דילמא כיון דמפקיד דינא, Dilma kivan
demifkid dina, since that’s when judgment will be wrought, you know, especially
because before we said the first three hours of the day God
sits and learns תורה, the second three hours God sits in judgment.
But right now we’re assuming judgment is in the beginning of the
day, and presumably also judgment associated with מוסף Musaf because... מוסף Musaf
is the central prayer of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, it's מלכויות, Malchiyos,
זכרונות, Zichronos, and שופרות, Shofros, so don't have that whole focus of
judgment and there you are, you're a יחיד, yachid, you're not doing
it as part of the ציבור, tzibbur, so you're also standing by
yourself, so don't do it at that time because that is the
greatest time of judgment and you're exposing yourself to the most danger.
דילמא מעייני בעובדי, dilma me'ayni be'uvdai, they will inspect your deeds, ודחפו
ליה מדחיי vedachfu lei midchayei and you'll be pushed off, you know,
you'll come out suffering from the judgment, you'll be found guilty. So
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי דציבור נמי, ee hachi detzibbur nami, if
that's true then even the congregation shouldn't דאוון davven מוסף Musaf that
early on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. I don't know what shul they
were going to that they could get to מוסף Musaf by three
hours into the day. So גמרא Gemara says דציבור נפישי זכותיה. detzibbur
nefishei zechusei. No, by its when you דאוון davven in the ציבור
tzibbur you have a lot of merit and therefore you are, that
will protect you even when you דאוון davven that early. אי הכי
דיחיד דצפרא נמי לא? ee hachi deyachid detzafra nami lo? So if
that's true, so then why shouldn't even שחרית Shacharis on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah you shouldn't דאוון davven during the first three hours of
the day, which is obviously the time to דאוון? davven? No, כיון
דכי ציבורא קא מצלו לא קא מדחו. keivan dechi tzibura ka matzlu
lo ka midchu. No, no, no, because everybody is דאוונינג davvening שחרית
Shacharis during the first three hours of the day, so you even
if you're דאוונינג davvening at home, you're connected to the prayers of
the ציבור. tzibbur. But מוסף, Musaf, most people don't get up to
מוסף Musaf that early, so if you're home, you know, when you're
at home you דאוון davven quicker usually, especially on ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, there's so much in the ציבור, tzibbur, off all you had
to do was דאוון davven at home, you'd go through it a
lot quicker. So therefore if you're up to מוסף Musaf in the
first three hours of the day, most of the, in the shuls
they're not up to מוסף. Musaf. So then you're really sort of
seen as standing alone and you don't want to stand alone in
judgment, especially, particularly during that period which is the period of judgment.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says והאמרת, veha'amarta, but didn't you
say שלש שעות ראשונות הקדוש ברוך הוא יושב ועוסק בתורה? shalosh sha'os
rishonos hakadosh baruch hu yoshev ve'osek batorah? The first three hours God's
learning תורה. So it says איפוך, eifoch, alright, reverse it. The first
three hours He's sitting in judgment, the second three He's learning תורה.
ואיבעית אימא לעולם לא תיפוך, ve'iba'is eima le'olam lo seifoch, don't reverse
it. תורה דכתיב בה אמת, Torah dechsiv bah emes, תורה's the truth.
דכתיב אמת קנה ואל תמכור, dechsiv emes kneh ve'al timkor, buy truth
and don't sell it, right, meaning be prepared to pay for your
education but you teach others, you know, for free. So, so תורה's
the truth. אין הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה לפנים משורת הדין. ein hakadosh
baruch hu oseh lifnim mishuras hadin. When God is learning תורה, it's
interesting, even though He's not sitting in judgment, but if you're sort
of praying to God while God is learning תורה, it's true also
like if you ever go into a בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, right,
like don't talk in a בית מדרש Beis Medrash about, oh, human
compassion and being nice, whatever, like no, it's all about pure argument,
you know, argue your side, argue the other side, it's like not
when somebody comes to you for a פסק הלכה. psak halacha. When
it comes to a פסק הלכה, psak halacha, we can be a
little flexible, we can rely on שיטות shitos we normally don't, wouldn't
agree with, you know, because it's about, it's about dealing with the
human being as opposed to the תורה, it's all about sort of
arguing like, you know, and finding the truth. So if you try
to talk to God while God's in the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash,
okay, you're not going to get too much flexibility. Alright. So אין
הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה לפנים משורת הדין. ein hakadosh baruch hu oseh
lifnim mishuras hadin. דין דלא כתיב ביה אמת, din dela kseiv bei
emes, when it comes to judgment which it doesn't have to be
about truth, you can be about compassion, judgment is about applying the
law to the human reality, it's not about some abstract philosophical truth.
So it doesn't have to, so therefore it can be a little
bit more flexible. Okay. דלא כתיב ביה, dela kseiv bei,
so in that case הקדוש ברוך הוא עושה לפנים משורת הדין, hakadosh
baruch hu oseh lifnim mishuras hadin, God could like, you know, not
do the exact judgment, God could find a little bit more latitude.
Okay, so it's better to deal with God when God is actually
sitting in judgment than when God is learning תורה. Quite ironic, but
I certainly understand exactly the, not scenario, the type of dynamic or
reality that the גמרא is describing. Okay, we will end here for
today.